{"author": "Robert R. Harr","data": [{"chapter": "1.3","questions": [{"data": [{"choices": ["Increased hemolysis","Decreased hemolysis","Normal resistance to hemolysis","Decreased hemolysis after incubation at 37°C"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Decreased hemolysis","explanation": "Osmotic fragility is decreased because numerous target cells are present and have increased surface volume in patients with thalassemia major."},"question": "The osmotic fragility test result in a patient with thalassemia major would most likely show:","reference": "Hematology/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/Microscopic morphology/Osmotic fragility/1"},{"choices": ["Microcytic, hypochromic RBC morphology","Decreased serum iron and ferritin levels","Decreased total iron-binding capacity (TIBC)","Increased RBC protoporphyrin"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Decreased total iron-binding capacity (TIBC)","explanation": "In IDA, there is an increase in TIBC and in RBC protoporphyrin. Serum iron and ferritin levels are decreased. IDA is characterized by a microcytic hypochromic anemia."},"question": "All of the following are characteristic findings in a patient with IDA except:","reference": "Hematology/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/Anemia/Iron deficiency/2"},{"choices": ["Serum iron level","RBC morphology","RBC indices","TIBC"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "TIBC","explanation": "In IDA, serum iron and ferritin levels are decreased, and TIBC and RBC protoporphyrin are increased. In chronic disease, serum iron and TIBC are both decreased because the iron is trapped in reticuloendothelial (RE) cells and is unavailable to RBCs for Hgb production."},"question": "IDA may be distinguished from anemia of chronic infection by:","reference": "Hematology/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize health and disease states/Anemia/3"},{"choices": ["Sickle cell anemia","Thalassemia syndrome","Pernicious anemia","HS"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Thalassemia syndrome","explanation": "Thalassemia and IDA are both classified as microcytic, hypochromic anemias. IDA is caused by defective heme synthesis, whereas thalassemia is caused by decreased globin chain synthesis."},"question": "Which anemia has RBC morphology similar to that seen in IDA?","reference": "Hematology/Correlate laboratory data with other laboratory data to assess test results/Anemia/RBC microscopic morphology/2"},{"choices": ["Decreased plasma iron, decreased % saturation, increased TIBC","Decreased plasma iron, decreased plasma ferritin, normal RBC porphyrin","Decreased plasma iron, decreased % saturation, decreased TIBC","Decreased plasma iron, increased % saturation, decreased TIBC"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Decreased plasma iron, decreased % saturation, increased TIBC","explanation": "IDA is characterized by decreased plasma iron, increased TIBC, decreased % saturation, and microcytic, hypochromic anemia. Iron deficiency occurs in three phases: iron depletion, iron-deficient erythropoiesis, and IDA."},"question": "IDA is characterized by:","reference": "Hematology/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize health and disease states/Anemia/Iron deficiency/2"},{"choices": ["Serum transferrin levels","Hgb values","Myoglobin values","Serum ferritin levels"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Serum ferritin levels","explanation": "Ferritin enters serum from all ferritin-producing tissues and, therefore, is considered a good indicator of body storage iron. Because iron stores must be depleted before anemia develops, low serum ferritin levels precede the fall in serum iron associated with IDA."},"question": "Storage iron is usually best determined by:","reference": "Hematology/Apply knowledge of basic laboratory procedures/Iron/1"},{"choices": ["Increased serum iron","Ringed sideroblasts","Hypochromic anemia","Decreased serum ferritin"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Decreased serum ferritin","explanation": "Sideroblastic anemias are a group of disorders characterized by hypochromic anemia, ineffective erythropoiesis, an increase in serum and tissue iron, and the presence of ringed sideroblasts in bone marrow."},"question": "All of the following are associated with sideroblastic anemia except:","reference": "Hematology/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize health and disease states/Anemia/Sideroblastic/2"},{"choices": ["DNA synthetic defect","Hgb structure","β-chain synthesis","Hgb phosphorylation"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "β-chain synthesis","explanation": "In thalassemia major, there is little or no production of the β-chain, resulting in severely depressed or no synthesis of Hgb A. Severe anemia is seen, along with skeletal abnormalities and marked splenomegaly. The patient is usually supported with transfusion therapy."},"question": "What is the basic hematological defect seen in patients with thalassemia major?","reference": "Hematology/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Hemoglobinopathy/1"},{"choices": ["Hgb D", "Hgb A", "Hgb C", "Hgb F"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Hgb F","explanation": "Patients with thalassemia major are unable to synthesize the β-chain; hence, little or no Hgb A is produced. However, γ-chains continue to be synthesized and lead to variable elevations of Hgb F in these patients."},"question": "Which of the following is the primary Hgb in patients with thalassemia major?","reference": "Hematology/Correlate clinical and laboratory diseases/Hemoglobin/Hemoglobinopathy/2"},{"choices": ["Normocytic, normochromic","Macrocytic, hypochromic","Microcytic, hypochromic","Normocytic, hyperchromic"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Microcytic, hypochromic","explanation": "The indices will provide a morphological classification of this anemia. MCV is 75 fL (reference range 80–100 fL), MCH is 20 pg (reference range 27–31 pg), and MCHC is 26.6% (reference range 32%–36%). Therefore, the anemia is microcytic hypochromic."},"question": "A patient has an Hct of 30%, an Hgb of 8 g/dL, and a RBC count of 4.0 × 1012/L. What morphological classification of this anemia?","reference": "Hematology/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize health and disease states/Hemoglobinopathy/Characteristics/3"},{"choices": ["Hgb H","Hgb SC disease","β-thalassemia minor","Hgb S trait"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "β-thalassemia minor","explanation": "Hgb A<sub>2</sub> is part of the normal complement of adult Hgb. This Hgb is elevated in β-thalassemia minor because the individual with this condition has only one normal β-gene; consequently, there is a slight elevation of Hgb A<sub>2</sub> and Hgb F."},"question": "In which of the following conditions is Hgb A2 elevated?","reference": "Hematology/Correlate laboratory results with disease states/2"},{"choices": ["Normocytic indices","Decreased serum iron concentration","Ringed sideroblasts","Pappenheimer bodies"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Decreased serum iron concentration","explanation": "Thirty to fifty percent of the individuals with anemia of chronic inflammation demonstrate a microcytic hypochromic blood picture, with decrease in serum iron. Serum iron is decreased because it is unable to escape from the RE cells to be delivered to the NRBCs in bone marrow."},"question": "Which of the following parameters may be similar for the anemia of inflammation and IDA?","reference": "Hematology/Correlate laboratory data to recognize health and disease states/2"}],"type": "MULTIPLE_CHOICE"}],"topic": "Hypochromic and Microcytic Anemias"}],"edition": "5th","title": "Medical Laboratory Science Review"}